Finding aid for the Experiments in Art and Technology records, 1966-1993 (bulk 1966-1973)
Experiments in Art and Technology records
Cross, Lowell M.; Childs, Lucinda; Cage, John; Brown, Trisha, 1936-2017; Breer, Robert; Davis, Douglas, 1933-2014; Tudor, David, 1926-1996; Tomkins, Calvin, 1925-; Whitman, Robert, 1935-; Waldhauer, Fred D.; Rainer, Yvonne, 1934-; Pearce, John; Shunk, Harry; Rauschenberg, Robert, 1925-2008; Moore, Peter, 1932-1993; Nakaya, Fujiko; Paik, Nam June, 1932-2006; Paxton, Steve; Kender, Janos; Klüver, Billy, 1927-2004; Martin, Julie, 1938-; Minujin, Marta, 1943-; Fahlström, Öyvind, 1928-1976; Garmire, Elsa M., 1939-; Hultén, Pontus, 1924-2006; Kaprow, Allan; Experiments in Art and Technology (Organization); Experiments in Art and Technology Los Angeles (Organization)
Container List
- Project files, 1966-1992, 1966-1973; Series I.; 112.5 lin. ft. 121 boxes, 7 flat file folders, 1 roll
  Arranged in rough chronological order by project. Includes organizational and fund-raising correspondence with museum directors, industry leaders and foundations, and between staff members; letters of inquiry, membership forms and project proposals, many with photographs and some with drawings, from artists and engineers who were interested in participating; E.A.T. proposals and reports, usually produced to attract sponsors and members; collected research material in the form of photocopied articles, government and foundation reports, brochures, equipment catalogs and clippings, especially pertaining to television and video; manuscripts; and notes by Klüver, Julie Martin and other E.A.T. staff. Especially well documented are "9 Evenings: Theatre and Engineering," 1966, the Pepsi Pavilion, 1970, the New York Collection for Stockholm, 1971-1973, and E.A.T.'s Technical Services Program. Notable participants in these and other activities are: Robert Breer, Trisha Brown, John Cage, Lucinda Childs, Lowell Cross, Douglas Davis, Öyvind Fahlström, Elsa Garmire, Pontus Hulten, Allan Kaprow, Marta Minujin, Fujiko Nakaya, Nam June Paik, John Pearce, Steve Paxton, Yvonne Rainer, Rauschenberg, David Tudor, Fred Waldhauer and Robert Whitman.
  - "9 Evenings: Theatre & Engineering,", 1966 (Box 1-1B)
    - Original manuscripts (unpublished and incomplete) (Box 1, Folder 1-19)
      material by or about most of the performers, including: Harriet De Long, Pontus Hulten, Steve Paxton, Alex Hay, Deborah Hay, Robert Rauschenberg, David Tudor, Yvonne Rainer, John Cage, Lucinda Childs, Robert Whitman and Öyvind Fahlström. Files contain original manuscript drafts, many with annotations, drawings by engineers, performance instructions by Rauschenberg, 2 signed scores by Tudor, instructions by Cage, and notes. There is a substantial quantity of photographs and slides by Peter Moore and others with detailed captions and layout instructions (see also Series VI. Photographs), ca. .5 lin. ft.
      - 0 Acknowledgement - 10 Carriage Discreteness (Box 1, Folder 1-10)
      - 11 Variations VII - 22 Documents (Box 1A, Folder 1-7)
      - Captions, miscellaneous, Dutton contracts (Box 1A, Folder 8-10)
    - MIT Press correspondence (Box 1A, Folder 11-12)
      primarily regarding lost portions of manuscript (1974-1976) and also includes a few miscellaneous letters (1966-1968). A separate folder contains a list of the missing manuscript portions, ca. 40 items, many photocopies.
    - Ms. copy (Box 1A-1B)
      photocopy of entire original manuscript, including missing sections, ca. .25 lin. ft.
      - 0 Aknowledgement - 6 Gross Fields (Box 1A, Folder 13-17)
      - 7 Solo - 22 Documents (Box 1B, Folder 1-17)
  - "9 Evenings,", 1966 (Box 2-2B)
    - Ms. copy (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
    - Ms. working copy (Box 2, Folder 4-7)
      contains typescripts with extensive notes and annotations.
      - Working copy, 1-3 of 4 (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
      - Working copy, 4 of 4 (Box 2A, Folder 1)
    - De Long material (Box 2A, Folder 2-4)
      primarily carbon copies of letters to artists requesting information about the performance and permission to reproduce material for the book, with some responses (see especially Simone Forti's notes for the old Tuscan song she sang between Rauschenberg's first and second performances). Also a 3 p. typescript telephone conversation with Grace Glueck, notes, drafts (see Box 50 for more) and miscellaneous, 1970-1973.
    - Index (Box 2A, Folder 5)
      list of materials contained in the following research files (O-X, E.A.T.'s numbering), but does not include everything.
    - Introduction (0) (Box 2A, Folder 6)
      background information in the form of clippings.
    - Artists (I) (Box 2A)
      descriptions of their pieces, comments, bios, announcements and some applicable correspondence with Cage, Childs, Fahlström, Deborah and Alex Hay, Paxton, Rainer, Rauschenberg, Tudor and Robert Whitman.
      - Folder 1 of 2 (Box 2A, Folder 7)
      - Folder 2 of 2 (Box 2B, Folder 1)
    - Engineers (II) (Box 2B, Folder 2)
      descriptions of their role in the performances.
    - Retrospect (III) (Box 2B, Folder 3-4)
      typescripts, some annotated, by Klüver, Robinson and Simone Whitman, and questionnaire responses from artists and engineers about the performances after-the-fact.
  - "9 Evenings,", 1966 (Box 3)
    - Interface (IV) (Box 3, Folder 1)
      consists of preparatory material for the Stockholm Festival, such as Klüver notes for texts and letters, many meeting notes with Rauschenberg, Fahlström, Cage and others (Mar 11, 1966-Aug 14, 1966), project lists, progress reports, bulletins, description of pieces and letter from Oldenburg (May 11, 1966).
    - Klüver (V) (Box 3, Folder 2-3)
      many mss. and some notes and copies of letters concerning the cancellation of the Stockholm Festival (for a good explanation see "Short Schedule of Events..." Jul 30, 1966), other mss. about ideas behind and purpose of "9 Evenings," and correspondence (ca. 20 items) with art critic Douglas Davis regarding interview published in Art in America.
    - Sweden Correspondence (VI) (Box 3, Folder 4-5)
      very extensive correspondence with Knut Wiggins of Fylkingen (modern music society) and some with others concerning the Stockholm Festival. Includes detailed descriptions from Frank and Susan Konigsberg about their meetings in Sweden with Wiggins concerning financial and organizational problems, ca. 125 items.
    - Telegrams (VII) (Box 3, Folder 6)
      30 items from Klüver to Cage, Tudor, Fahlström and others about organization.
    - Press (VIII) (Box 3, Folder 7-10)
      includes correspondence with editors, critics, sponsors and others about press coverage, press releases and briefings; radio and TV transcripts; substantial review clippings and copies of reviews; and copies of Swedish articles about Stockholm Festival, some with translation typescripts.
    - Correspondence, Agreements (IX) (Box 3, Folder 11)
      typescripts of agreements with the Armory, Foundation for Contemporary Performance Arts and the FCC.
    - Correspondence, Equipment and Accommodations (IX) (Box 3, Folder 12)
      with suppliers about obtaining technical equipment and air and hotel accommodations for Swedish Festival.
    - Correspondence, Financial (X) (Box 3, Folder 13)
      with sponsors and potential sponsors concerning donations, and with various companies after the event about unpaid bills (see also Box 4 and Series V. Financial).
    - Information requests (Box 3, Folder 14)
      notes from John Baldessari, Richard Hamilton, Jean Brown and others, ca. 65 items.
    - Interview transcripts (Folder 15)
      with Paxton, Deborah Hay, Alex Hay, Childs, Whitman, Trisha Brown and Bob Breer.
    - Robinson files (Box 3, Folder 16-21)
      on power amplifier; on E.A.T. projects with letter from Paik, other correspondence and drawings of circuits; description of Bonino show; organization of E.A.T.; manuscript "What Really Happened at the Armory"; and other.
    - Fahlström Files (Box 3, Folder 22-23)
      translation of "Armory" manuscript and 19 slides.
    - Maricla Moyano Files (Box 3, Folder 24)
      19 p. photocopied typescript and 5 photographs of "9 Evenings."
    - Rauschenberg Files (Box 3, Folder 25)
      includes 2 p. typescript instructions for "Open Score," 2 page fragment of a letter recruiting volunteers, and telexes.
    - Deborah Hay Files (Box 3, Folder 26)
      "Solo" notes.
  - "9 Evenings,", 1966 (Box 4)
    - Herb Schneider files (Box 4, Folder 1-7)
      includes correspondence and mss.; "APP" file with description of wireless system, Stockholm Festival schematics and layouts, address lists, correspondence with potential speakers and those interested in the festival, such as Marshall McLuhan, Buckminster Fuller and Nam June Paik; "Discussion 1966" files with clippings and 9 photographs by Moore and 7 by others; and engineering files relating to many of the performances with notes and circuit drawings; ca. .5 lin. ft.
    - Miscellaneous Klüver drafts (Box 4, Folder 8)
      includes mss. for Sep 29, 1966 press briefing, "Establishing an Interactive Relationship Between the Artist and Technology," and galley for "Art 1963-A New Vocabulary."
    - Memo to engineers (Box 4, Folder 12)
      describing artists and potential problems.
    - Film rental and photographorders (Box 4, Folder 13-14)
    - Financial (Box 4, Folder 15-17)
      accounting ledger (ca. 1963-1965), payroll and box office accounting (see also Box 3 and Box 164).
    - Early documents (Box 4, Folder 18)
      mostly photocopies of correspondence, reports and lists regarding organization and support for E.A.T. (1967) with a short handwritten statement by Rauschenberg.
    - Clippings and press releases (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Miscellaneous: mostly correspondence and notes (Box 4, Folder 20-21)
  - "9 Evenings,", 1966 (Box 5)
    - Tickets (Box 5, Folder 1-52)
      unused tickets and stubs with envelopes annotated as to type of ticket (i.e., paid, complimentary, press, discount), quantity and date.
  - Technical Services Program, 1966-1973 (Box 6)
    - Artists' proposals, 1968-1969 (Box 6, Folder 1-37)
      contains over 70 proposals filed in alpha order by artist, some with photographs and slides; drawings and/or schematics; bios with miscellaneous typescripts and clippings; E.A.T. correspondence with corporations for funding; correspondence between E.A.T. or the artist and engineers/scientists with technical comments; and patent information.
      Includes proposals by John Cage (with handwritten notes); Sari Dienes (with 5 photos, correspondence and Poole notes); Ruth Francken (correspondence, proposal in 2 drafts dated May 8, 1968 with 1 photograph of maquette, and Feb 19, 1969 with drawing and 2 photos); Philip Glass (with correspondence, bio information including flyers and announcements, and 2 photos); Allan Kaprow (with correspondence and budget sheets); Marta Minujin ("Phone Booth" with 7 photos; "Simultaneity in Simultaneity" with 2 p. statement, 5 photos, and 1 photo-collage with text; "Circuit and Instantaneous Invasion" includes correspondence, 3 p. description and 2 drawings [see Box 50]; and "Minucode" press release and questionnaire); Alan Sondheim; Jean Toche; Jud Yalkut among many others; ca. .5 lin. ft.
    - Artists' membership forms, 1967-1969, 1968-1969 (Box 6, Folder 38-48)
      mostly forms filled out by artists many with descriptions of their work and/or the technical assistance they require. Some include photos, slides, bios and drawings, from such artists as: Mel Bochner, Fahlström, Nancy Graves, Alice Hutchins, Hans Haacke (form and sheet with description and drawing for "photo-electrically sensitized 'environment'"), Deborah Hay, Al Hansen, Eva Hesse, Geoffrey Hendricks, Joe Jones, Udo Kasemets, Allan Kaprow, Alison Knowles, Gordon Mumma (plus letter about borrowing Schilling's 9 Evenings film and equipment needs), Meredith Monk, Peter Moore, Jackson MacLow, Phill Niblock, Brian O'Doherty, Lil Picard, George Rickey (letter), Larry Rivers, Carolee Schneemann (plus bio), Richard Serra, Elaine Sturtevant, Alan Sondheim, James Tenney, Emmett Williams and Jud Yalkut, filed in rough alpha order, ca. .5 lin. ft.
  - Technical Services Program, 1966-1973 (Box 7)
    - Artists' membership forms, 1967-1970 (Box 7, Folder 1-18)
      similar material to Box 6. 1967-1968 files contain photocopies, ca. .25 lin. ft. 1969 files include: Douglas Davis (2 forms, 2 letters, and photocopied bio, statement and equipment list) and Agnes Denes (2 forms, press release and photo). 1970 files mostly have forms that were filled out in 1969, but were not acted upon until 1970.
  - Technical Services Program, 1966-1973 (Box 8)
    - Engineers' membership forms, 1967-1970, 1968-1969 (Box 8, Folder 1-17)
      forms filled out by engineers/scientists describing their interests and technical expertise, filed in rough alpha order within date, ca. .75 lin. ft.
    - Others' membership forms, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Technical Services Program, 1966-1973 (Box 9)
    - Artists' and engineers' membership forms, 1970 (Box 9, Folder 1-2)
      photocopies.
    - Matchings, 1966-1970, 1968-1969 (Box 9, Folder 3-23)
      mostly artists' membership forms, proposals (some with photographs and slides and a few with drawings) and inquiries, by artists such as Robert Barry, Carol Bergé, Philip Corner, Dan Flavin (3 p. handwritten letter), Robert Filliou, Ruth Francken, Allen Ginsberg, Dick Higgins, Alison Knowles, Robert Morris, Richard Nonas, Lucio Pozzi, Richard Serra, Mark di Suvero, Alan Sondheim, Twyla Tharp and Ultra Violet. Some are annotated as to when a match was made. 1968-1969 filed in rough alpha order, ca. .75 lin. ft.
    - Notes on matchings, 1966-1968 (Box 9, Folder 24-27)
      Miscellaneous meeting and other notes.
  - Technical Services Program, 1966-1973 (Box 10)
    - Membership inquiries, 1967-1974, 1967-1971 (Box 10, Folder 1-18)
      letters and postcards expressing interest in membership, subscriptions and general information from artists, engineers, museum personnel, professors, librarians, with carbon copies of responses from E.A.T. staff. Also contains some dues invoices.
  - Technical Services Program, 1966-1973 (Box 11)
    - Miscellaneous membership (Box 11, Folder 1-16)
      draft letters and forms; membership drive meeting notes (1970-1971); letters to corporations; projects for industry; participation categories; kit; proposal review letters; engineering consultant ideas; solicitation samples; symbolic coding forms; notched cards (see also Box 14); and punch codes.
    - Miscellaneous Technical Services (Box 11, Folder 17-26)
      includes correspondence; IEEE Convention file (1968); computer resource material; and miscellaneous photographs and slides (22 photos; 7 slides; 3 transparencies).
    - Ralph Flynn's address and schedule books, 1968 (Box 11, Folder 27-28)
  - Technical Services Program, equipment files, includes:, 1968 (Box 12)
    - Correspondence (Box 12, Folder 1-4)
      primarily about equipment with a letter from Jackson MacLow concerning equipment setup (Feb 15, 1968), ca. 80 items.
    - Equipment information (Box 12, Folder 5-49)
      includes catalogs; brochures; fliers and correspondence with 2 letters from Dan Flavin about convincing the Whitney Museum board that the use of long-wave ultra-violet light in one of his works is safe for public viewing (see safety); filed in alpha order by equipment type; ca. .5 lin. ft.
    - Artists' projects (Box 12, Folder 50-57)
      includes 4 files with action taken on them (includes proposal by Kaprow and file on Robert Morris).
    - Rauschenberg's Stedelijk show, 1968 (Box 12, Folder 58-59)
      extensive quantity of equipment receipts; many drawings of circuitry; and some notes.
    - Financial (Box 12, Folder 60-62)
      equipment expense receipts and NSF fund-raising material.
  - Technical Services Program, 1966-1973 (Box 13)
    5x8 cards of early technical sources for the E.A.T. publications "Technical Libraries within 50 mile radius of New York" by Peter Poole. Also "collaboration response cards" on which the artist or engineer provided information on the progress of their collaboration.
  - Technical Services Program, 1966-1973 (Box 14)
    7 1/2 x 3 1/2 Yellow McBee Edge-notched cards with names of engineer members and notations of artists they were matched with on back.
    Blue MacBee keysort edge-notched cards with encoded information for a data-base of Engineers.
  - Technical Services Program, membership mailing lists, 1967-1974 (Box 15-16)
    Extensive quantity of mailing lists of artist and engineer members typed on labels or photocopied, 1967-1974. See also Boxes 17-23 for index cards.
  - Technical Services Program, membership mailing lists, 1968 (Box 17)
    8x5 index cards with addresses of engineers who contacted E.A.T. in 1968, and of schools and universities, journals, research centers and professional engineering societies.
  - Technical Services Program, membership mailing lists, 1967 (Box 18-23)
    Ca. 2400 3x5 index cards organized into American, Foreign, Artists (9 Evenings) and Corporations, 1967.
  - E.A.T. Competition, includes:, 1967 (Box 24)
    - Entry list (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - Information forms (Box 24, Folder 3-8)
      filled out by artists, such as Hans Haacke, Claire Falkenstein, Steve Paxton, Robert Whitman and La Monte Young, with brief project descriptions and by engineers/scientists listing their capabilities/interests. Also folders with artist/engineer matches and unmatched artists and engineers, ca. .25 lin. ft.
    - Inquiries (Box 24, Folder 9-15)
      extensive quantity of brief correspondence from artists, such as Falkenstein, Dennis Oppenheim and Dan Graham, engineers and others requesting information about the competition and E.A.T. in general, ca. .5 lin. ft.
    - Competition winners (Box 24, Folder 16)
      project descriptions of the nine winners and bios.
    - Jury and prize donors: includes jury instructions and list, and donor correspondence (Box 24, Folder 17)
    - Press information (Box 24, Folder 18)
      mostly press releases, announcements and mailing lists.
  - Some More Beginnings, 1968-1969 (Box 25-25B)
    - Artist and engineer entry lists (Box 25, Folder 1-4)
    - Index cardfile of entries (Box 25, Folder 5)
    - Project descriptions (Box 25-25B)
      primarily artistic and technical descriptions of ca. 128 (including Box 26) of the ca. 145 works exhibited at the Brooklyn Museum, used in preparation for the catalog. Most with bios and one or more photographs, and some with correspondence and drawings (see especially Ruth Francken, Amy Hamouda and Leah Nolan), .75 lin. ft.
      - Adams - Costa (Box 25, Folder 6-25)
      - Delaney - Hoener (Box 25A, Folder 1-25)
      - Intersystems - Lujan (Box 25B, Folder 1-23)
  - Some More Beginnings, 1968-1969 (Box 26-26B)
    - Project descriptions (Box 26-26B)
      - Marcus - Rievschl (Box 26, Folder 1-22)
      - Richter - Venet (Box 26A, Folder 1-28)
      - Venezia - Whitman, miscellaneous (Box 26B, Folder 1-11)
    - Applications, A-D (Box 26B, Folder 12-15)
      contains mostly photocopies of information forms (originals in box 24) and project descriptions (originals in boxes 25-26), but, includes a few originals of these documents and original drawings, correspondence and photos, .25 lin. ft.
  - Some More Beginnings, includes:, 1968-1969 (Box 27)
    - Applications, E-Z (Box 27, Folder 1-20)
      see above, .5 lin. ft.
    - Correspondence (Box 27, Folder 21-23)
      with artists and others about various matters, such as reproductions; shipping; thank-yous; catalog and information requests, including a letter from Dennis Young, Art Gallery of Ontario, inquiring if there were any mechanical problems with the art works (see also Box 41, laser safety); letter from Eastman & Eastman attorneys about Wen-Ying Tsai receiving improper credit for his contribution to the second place winning entry with Klüver's response; 2 letters regarding Ronald Fox's stolen work; and a note from Claire Falkenstein (ca. 100 items). Separate files contain carbons of letters to Pontus Hulten and some correspondence with his staff about various competition details.
    - Catalog (Box 27, Folder 24-27)
      fund-raising correspondence, drafts, photograph credits and orders.
    - Public Relations (Box 27, Folder 28-31)
      includes press releases for E.A.T. press conference and Brooklyn and MOMA exhibitions, exhibition announcements, MOMA press packet and background information
    - Technical needs (Box 27, Folder 32)
      summary notes and log.
    - Miscellaneous (Box 27, Folder 34-36)
      includes freight invoices, correspondence and list concerning some works traveling to other venues, and long computer printout "Sculptures in Environment Douglas Gallery."
  - Lecture-Demonstration Series, 1968 (Box 28)
    - Response forms (Box 28, Folder 1-9)
      extensive quantity from artists such as Ay-O, Jo Baer, Marisol, Fahlström, Dan Graham, Hans Haacke, Deborah Hay, Eva Hesse, Dennis Oppenheim, Paik, Richard Serra, Jack Tworkov, Emmett Williams and others, specifying which lecture they want to attend.
    - Transcripts (Box 28, Folder 10-34)
      24 unpublished transcripts, some annotated, of reel-to-reel tapes recorded at the lectures given by engineers such as Ken Knowlton, James Tenney (with 2 contact sheets and negs.) and Max Mathews (with 2 contact sheets by Peter Moore); ca. .66 lin. ft.
    - Correspondence (Box 28, Folder 35-36)
      includes organizational notebook, letters to and from lecturers, and letter from Marisol.
    - Miscellaneous (Box 28, Folder 37-42)
      includes schedules; 5 contact sheets (3 by Moore), 1 photograph and 3 negs.; illustrative material in the form of 22 photos, matching transparencies and drawings of diagrams; and technical services proposal draft.
  - Local Groups, includes:, ca. 1966-ca. 1970, undated (Box 29)
    - National organization plans (Box 29, Folder 1-3)
      documents regarding policy, by-laws and structure.
    - Correspondence (Box 29, Folder 4-5)
      mostly inquires and contact letters, ca. 70 items.
    - Newsletters (Box 29, Folder 6)
      from local groups, ca. 35 items.
    - U.S. files (Box 29, Folder 7-65)
      includes much organizational correspondence; an inquiry from James Turrell (Calif., L.A.); mailing lists; meeting minutes and notes; filed alpha by state, ca. .75 lin. ft, 1/3 of which was generated by Calif.
  - Local Groups, ca. 1967-ca. 1970 (Box 30)
    - International files (Box 30, Folder 1-22)
      Mostly organizational correspondence, but also contains a copy of a letter from Marcel Broodthaers to Joseph Beuys in praise of his work, filed alpha by country, ca. .25 lin. ft.
    - Mailing lists (Box 30, Folder 23-29)
      U.S. and International, filed alpha by state or country.
    - First Int'l. Conference, Jun 22, 1968-Jun 23, 1968 (Box 30, Folder 30-38)
      ideas; some correspondence; RSVP's; roster and planning; program; transcript; local group procedures; VIP invitation addresses; and notes on Second Int'l Conference; ca. .25 lin. ft.
  - Mailing lists, undated (Box 31-39)
    4500-5000 3x5 index cards arranged into groups of artists and engineers master files, filed alphabetically, and into Local Groups, filed alpha by state or country.
  - Video and television research, 1969-1972 (Box 40)
    - Video and television projects (Box 40, Folder 1-15)
      Contains various materials concerning video and television including artists' project proposals for residence program at RCA labs (with 1 letter from Paik and 1 from Bruce Conner); information on education; reports concerning development of video equipment (e.g.: editing systems, camera, scanning and methods of transferring Super 8 film to video); and studies and bulletins on cable television from Wilbur Schramm, Rand and others